All right, welcome. My name's Derek
Radney. I'm a pastor
of Trinity in Winston-Salem, North
Carolina. And this is the AMR sort of
General Assembly recap. We had the 50th
General Assembly that finished pretty
early today before dinner on Thursday
night at General Assembly.
We have a new stated clerk in the
Presbyterian Church in America under
Fred Greco.
We had 90 overtures come to the General
Assembly this year, the most we've ever
had
by a lot. And we probably get through
that business. We had clicker-gate, a
lot of problems with voting machines. We
have two study committees that were
continued to do their work, and we added
a third study committee on top of that.
So
a lot of things took place
at this General Assembly, but we thought
we'd just take some time to just reflect
a little bit on on everything that went
down. So I've got with me Jeff Zigler
from Western Springs
>> Trinity Presbyterian Church
>> Yeah, Trinity. And Eric Bonkowski at
City Church in Richmond.
And so Jeff is on the governing board of
AMR,
and Eric's on the content team of AMR
with me. And so been helping with the
vision statement and all the articles
that have been written and the stuff
we've been producing. So we're just
going to take some time to reflect on
the General Assembly. I thought I'd
start with you, Jeff, and just ask you
to share with us some of your thoughts
on how how the week went.
>> Sure. I mean I think I think we've
already mentioned the thing that
probably everyone will be remembering
and talking about, that's clicker-gate,
right? The fact that anytime we had to
come to a decision that was at all
close, it usually would have like voice
vote or standing up, and then division
would be called because no one would
know exactly what was, and then we'd do
the clicks. And
so it seemed like, given that we had 90
overtures, two, you know, study
committees that were supposed to be big
ones coming up, like it no one I think
would have been predicting or saying and
every decision's going to take 15
minutes long. Yeah. That we would be
doing this right now.
>> Yeah.
>> But I think what's kind of striking is
that
that that isn't what happened. That
there was kind of a a kind of a
collaboration that I took I think took
place.
Um
>> And ClickerGate offered to us this
wonderful living analogy for
Presbyterianism.
>> Yeah. Right. Right.
>> It's frustrating. It takes a long time.
It requires lots of patience from
everyone involved. And yet in the end it
works out.
>> Yep.
>> And and actually the the slowness, the
frustratingness, was actually like again
like Presbyterianism. I think actually
works to our benefit. Like I think you
had pointed out to me that, you know, in
kind of like in the same way that like
if an entire town is dealing with some
sort of disaster they kind of come
together. It did feel like we were kind
of coming together around how are we
going to do this?
>> And we talked about in the Assembly
Hall, right? That as the votes were
taking 3 minutes or 5 minutes long guys
were talking to each other, laughing
about it in in a way that was fostering
this collegiality that's often absent
from the assembly.
>> Yes. The potential frustration at maybe
each other was being directed to a
common enemy.
>> But I think so yes. And I think that
actually like I said, you know, one of
the expectations was long. I think
another
bit of apprehension people were having
is that GAs in the last four or five
years there have been a number that felt
contentious, felt like we had kind of
have increasingly
disparate kind of positions that are
kind of pulling us apart. I think people
were feeling very discouraged. That is
not what I would say leaving was my kind
of experience that um it seemed there
was more of a collaborative spirit, more
of trust. I mean, if you think about
some of the votes there like were there
overtures? I'm pointing to you cuz Eric
was in overtures. Or just in the floor,
almost all of the ones we kind of
decided pretty broadly. I And the
decisions that we made I can't think of
times that we were really changing the
boundaries at all. This was just kind of
like trying to navigate some complicated
stuff like original jurisdiction. That's
something that like there's an example
like for 15 years we've been talking
about how to solve this part of the BCO
where if a Presbytery doesn't do what
it's supposed to do, how do we get SJC
to get involved and we haven't figured
it out. That came through. So it was a
time actually if anything I feel like
trust maybe felt a little bit greater
between us.
>> Um I think that
this year as often happens with GA there
can be a high level of anxiety going
into GA whether that's felt by pastors
or ruling elders or even people in the
local congregations. I picked up on some
of that and even had received questions
about what's going to happen with this
or you know, is what's the future of the
PCA and I think now on the backside of
GA we feel encouraged about the
denomination because
that anxiety ahead of time wasn't
warranted. What what we discovered in
fact was this higher level of trust and
collaboration working together.
>> Even even something as simple as like
the nominations like the nominating
committee did a lot of work, came with
their nominations and almost every
single one the nomination like okay, we
trust you. We're going to go with that
which is different from how it's been in
the last few years.
>> Yeah, there was a lot of deferring to
the committees.
>> Yep.
>> Uh whether it was a richers or RPR for
the most part we agreed with everything
they recommended with one exception. Um
committee of commissioners there were a
few questions and you know, potential
controvert for the most part there was a
lot of unity in the committee of
commissioners and then there was a lot
of agreement by the floor with the
committee of commissioners.
>> Which is how it has to work. There's no
way that we on the floor can make all
these decisions. We have to trust our
committees to be able to do this well.
>> So despite all the noise kind of coming
in, it seemed like actually people came
in and were ready to trust each other
and work together. That was a big thing.
>> Right. And I would say another it it's
not just we're trusting the committees
but that as committees in the committee
of commissioners are doing their
important work of reviewing control to
us. And so it's not squashing or
diminishing reviewing control, but it's
allowing it to have its place in the
midst of trust.
>> Yeah. So this brings me to like another
kind of reflection that I was having
where I feel like
another thing you could say you could
see is the triumph of I guess you could
say statesmanship or or being churchman
over online agitators. So you know,
there's there's a lot of noise is going
on
online with with Twitter or X whatever
you want to call it where and of course
that always rewards the more
contentious, the more polarizing, the
more angry it gets.
Um but what actually happening here in
the Presbyterian like I think about what
happened at GA. What happened was a
number of times the reason we were able
to do what we did and have the level of
trust that we're talking about is you
had people doing some really good work
face-to-face work. So like for example
overtures like I think the most we've
ever had was 63 and we had 90 here,
right? And so like how in the world were
we going to get through it? Well, you
know, there were you know, I think
Howie, you know, like you know, a couple
of guys that we know working together,
working through how are we going to get
a docket that makes sense. And also
navigating how are we going to navigate
all of these questions related to the
diaconal roles
so that then the overtures committee I
think felt like yeah, this makes sense.
This is good. They were able to move
through that really quickly and
effectively. Or I think go ahead.
>> I would add to that like you mentioned
statesmanship, but what's behind
statesmanship is statesman, right? It It
It happens at individual level, a
personal level and
I don't think we need to name names, but
there are some of the leaders of the
denomination who live that out. And and
they do that in a relational way that
rather than seeking to take someone down
online, they're taking them out to a
meal or they're hosting a dinner before
the assembly starts to work through some
of these issues. And I think when we're
closing the distance on some of the
contentious issues that leads to
effective work.
>> That's right. And this is this is you
know like this is one of the reasons why
I think it was Howie Donahue that wrote
that article about trust for us for our
kind of theological vision.
And
you cannot do Presbyterianism without
that. And the way that you develop trust
is exactly that kind of thing where it's
that face-to-face.
And so whether we're talking about that
or there's you know we talked about
original jurisdiction. This is something
that we've been trying to figure out for
15 years. Well, you have two guys who
are kind of figuring out a compromise,
you know like who and that allows us as
a denomination to be able to to work
together. So this is just that kind of
thoughtful, slow, you know like like
unexciting hard work as opposed to like
you know like when you have the months
before GA the only thing that we're
really experiencing is the online
chatter. And so it can feel like the
voices there are actually the ones who
are shaping things that are powerful.
But I can think of like you know even
like an example like there were there
were some chatter online and emails and
that kind of thing about trying to kind
of do a maneuver today related to the
whole deacon compromise what not. And it
ended up being like you had one overture
that was pulled out. No one even had a
chance to speak to it because they
didn't have any speeches. It was it was
nothing. So you see the power and the
strength of people working face-to-face
and the ephemeral kind of nothingness of
what's being just shouted online. And it
just it was really helpful to see that.
Um
>> Yeah, I mean I think coming into the
General Assembly a lot of questions were
raised about officers and the role of
women in our church and the
And [snorts]
what we saw is essentially everyone
saying where where the PCA has been
we're comfortable with where we are.
>> Yes.
>> Uh there were a lot of formal like 40-5s
filed throughout this year and through
review and control those things were
looked into by Presbyteries and then I
know from our PR they looked at those
things and
and what what came out of all this is
essentially a statement that we're okay,
the boundaries are clear, and there are
things that maybe need to get handled,
but those can get handled on Presbytery
levels,
and we we trust each other, we're going
to keep moving forward, and this really
doesn't need to to have the the uproar
that it had online.
>> Well, and I I think even from the
perspective of overtures, if you go back
and look at some of the way that
overtures were answered, a lot of the
grounds that the overtures committee
gave were this is already addressed
within
>> That's right, institution. Don't need to
say anything additional because what
we've said in in our confession, in our
constitution as a church is enough.
>> Yes.
>> Um to serve the churches, to serve the
Presbytery.
>> And we felt confidently Presbyterian,
right? Like recognizing we have courts,
we have structures, we have a Book of
Church Order, and this actually has the
stability that we need to be able to
navigate, rather than having to change
and react kind of reactively.
>> Yeah.
>> And I would say some of that is even
related to the sheer number of overtures
that we have.
>> We might as well attribute it to the
fact that 90 overtures came before the
overtures committee, which is far away
more than we've had before. And part of
what the overtures committee did,
intentionally and I think wisely, was to
say
we can't fully discuss and deliberate on
all of these. So, a number were answered
um by referring back to the
Presbyteries, or were answered in the
negative, and that has the effect of
saying um what we have is enough.
Confidently Presbyterian, we're
confidently confessional, and we don't
have to pedantically alter every line in
the BCO because we have this tradition
of interpretation that we can stand
upon.
>> I I'll just throw out one one thing that
David Coffin said um in our video where
we did the round table on overtures was
that the BCO amendment process has
typically been um at the end of a lot of
conversation about a particular issue
where there's been working together to
build consensus on what would be
fruitful changes.
And now a lot of these overtures are
being thrown up, you know, when just
someone has an idea of what could be
better. And I do hope that after this
assembly with so many being sent up,
there's a little bit more discretion
used by presbyteries and even in some
cases individuals to send stuff up
without having first done a lot of work
to kind of get the word out, talk with
others, and try to come with something
that already has a lot of people going
this would
>> be a good change.
>> building and I think it also um shows a
certain level of pragmatism about the
Presbyterian process. And that that was
another thing that some of the kind of
senior voices within the overtures
committee offered this year of a
pragmatic approach to Presbyterianism of
that this will not pass.
>> Yeah. Right. This won't pass
>> Let's not waste everyone's time.
>> pass the assembly or this certainly
won't pass two-thirds of the
presbyteries even if it does pass the
assembly. And so therefore let's focus
our attention and our work on things
that can pass and can advance
um the presby the the work of the
denomination.
>> Which is what you want. We want a
stability. Like we don't want like a
Book of Church Order that's always
changing. So I've committed myself to it
and now it's something different. We
want something that reflects kind of
this confident stable consensus that we
know it's not going to have to change in
a year's time.
>> And I think I very much hope that some
of the overtures that were referred back
or even ones that were answered in the
negative that we will see them again
either next year or in the future after
they've been refined and after
uh a single presbytery has done the work
of building consensus and maybe getting
together with a few other presbyteries
and saying, "How can we make this
better? How can we develop a an an
overture that actually will pass the
denomination and serve the
denomination?" And so I think some of
the overtures that dealt with um the
diaconal issue um fall into that
category. And there may be some people
who are frustrated. We've even heard it
from the floor today of people who are
who said, "Uh, listen, there there nine,
there 10 overtures that deal with this
issue. It's not settled within the PCA.
And so, there's appetite for talking
about it more, but uh, we need to refine
the way we're talking about it in in a
way that's reaching across different
groups within the the denomination."
>> And for precedent, I mean, we think
about some of the controversies of the
last decade and you can think of like,
for example, the study report that, you
know, Tim Keller and Kevin DeYoung
worked on same-sex attraction. And and
there were a number of attempts at
overtures and it took multiple years,
but then eventually we kind of came to a
stability that everyone was comfortable
with. And we haven't talked about it
again. And like, that's just the process
that has to work.
>> Um, did you have any other reflections?
>> Yeah, I was going to say, like we've
been talking only positive. There's one
part that I probably I mean, we're
always going to have things that we
feel, you know, differently about, like
we would have like to go a different. I
do think when we get to some of the RPR
stuff,
I think as a denomination, we're still
needing to think through how much how
much we want to make people who are far
removed from the decisions the ones who
are making the decisions and how much we
really want to trust the ones close by.
Cuz as I understand it, one of the key
ideas of the way that we work as a
denomination is subsidiarity. Saying,
for example, in in this particular case,
when a Presbytery is examining an
individual to see whether or not the
person's qualified to be ordained,
whether there's exceptions are
appropriate. We need to trust the people
who are who know the person, who like
the committees are meeting, you know,
can can answer credentials committee is
meeting with them for like a couple of
hours and defer to them except in
extraordinary circumstances or certain
obvious situations where things
And so, here we had uh, a minority
report discussion, right? Where we are,
you know, where there was a question
about whether a person held an exception
that or held a difference that could be
an allowable exception
uh, related to images of Jesus.
And and I think the discussion moved
from the question of
to what extent should we give deference
to the lower courts, which is really
what it was about, to what do we think
about the second commandments? And that
really isn't the discussion we're
supposed to be having at this place.
We're supposed to be
thinking about that that larger question
about what we're supposed to empower the
lower courts to do, what we're supposed
to kind of intervene. And that's
something I don't know how, but I would
love for us to be able to think how to
talk about that better because I think
it's a really important thing that we
need to navigate. Yeah.
>> Yeah, and I think that that's bringing
into relief for us one of the tensions
inherent within Presbyterianism, which
is
subsidiarity and the
um the process of review and control.
>> That's right.
>> That that's also a fundamental part of
what Presbyterianism means and no one is
rejecting the idea of review and
control, but uh for review and control
to work side by side with subsidiarity,
uh I think it requires trust. And one of
the fundamental
um vows that every elder in the PCA
takes is subjection to the brethren,
which is speaking to this issue of
trust. But it's hard to define what
trust looks like, what trust smells what
it smells like, right? When you're in
the midst of a debate or uh review of
Presbyterian records.
>> Yep.
>> Yeah, speaking of RPR, I would say this
this assembly rejected attempts to
reform RPR. That was a that was an
attempt.
>> So, there were two overtures in
different ways that sought to reform
RPR.
>> Yep.
>> Because RPR has
become very long as a report and there's
a lot going on. Um and there seems to be
a will, a desire to shorten what is
brought to the assembly. Um because, you
know, and I've been one of them, people
pulling things out of RPR to try to
address particular matters. And a lot of
people feel like we don't know what's
going on. We just want to trust the
committee, but then the committee's
giving us more and more stuff every
year. What do we do about this? And so,
there were some attempts at at um at
editing how we do that and those were
both rejected this year. So there
there's going to be need to be some more
work in looking into how can we do
review and control well. Yeah. Yeah.
Okay, any other thoughts that you had?
>> I have I have one more but it's probably
better for the end. I don't know if you
have anything else or
>> What about you Eric? You were on
overtures to that stand out to you in
your experience at all?
>> Yeah, I think it I think it is worth
mentioning a little bit of overtures.
We've talked about the sheer number of
overtures that came before us and so of
us who have served on overtures is a
full day on Monday, a full day on
Tuesday.
I've served on overtures before and the
amount of time that we spend together
was longer than I've ever spent before.
It's kind of the experience afterwards
of walking out of the the meeting room
as if you've been in a riding in a
convertible for 4 hours. You just feel
wind blown but I you know,
Presbyterianism
um
but what I will say is number one, the
committee was extremely well led by Guy
Waters.
>> Yes, he was amazing.
>> We can say the same about our moderator
for this year that Mel Duncan did a a
fantastic job of leading
>> High degree of difficulty, right? And he
was able to get yeah.
>> They can with with quicker gate.
>> That's right.
>> everything that was going on and so
I'm encouraged by the the resources we
have, the human resources that we have
in the denomination to help lead us
through these challenging issues. I will
say as well that one of the things that
stands out to me from overtures is one
of the very first overtures that we
talked about in past was an overture
that
gave thanks for the professions of faith
within
And I think sometimes in all of the
Presbyterianism that we do and all of
the the jargon and the lingo is we miss
the advancement of God's kingdom and the
advancement of God's mission through the
local church and through things like our
new law. So some of the highlights of
this assembly for me were
after the assembly passed that overture
containing time to pray in Thanksgiving
for
continued professions of faith in our
denomination and hearing reports from
RUF about
nearly 100 interns who are going to be
placed on campuses that is addressing
this very real problem of a leadership
pipeline for our denomination.
>> And I mean the report from Covenant
College, I mean just the encouragement
of what God is doing there and the
vision they had. I mean you're right.
Like like we don't get into the PCA so
we can go to GA, right? We get into the
PCA because this is the kind of stuff
we're excited about and seeing it was
really encouraging.
>> Yeah, I mean that would that would
probably be my biggest takeaway is that
the denomination and what we're doing,
there's a lot of really great things to
celebrate. And often that gets
overshadowed by online online arguments
and controversies and then overtures
that are trying to respond to that and
fix this or that. Uh but the but the
part of our General Assembly that often
gets overlooked that's kind of the most
exciting part is hearing about what our
seminary is doing, our college is doing,
what RUF is doing, what M&A is doing,
what Mission to the World is doing and
like, you know, there's great ministry
happening.
>> And and see the other thing maybe for
some of the people who are watching a
review or recap of GA that they wouldn't
see is it it's the interactions that we
get to have with one another. It's Yes.
The
the the conversations we have outside
the assembly hall or over meals. And one
of the things that I heard from multiple
people this year was this this admission
that despite our debates on the floor,
we what we share in common is 99% of
what we think and and the amount that we
debate is this thin sliver of 1% and I
think that can get missed sometimes in
in a review or when we're focusing issue
to issue.
>> Yeah, that's right. So on Monday night I
went to the Next Gen Forum that was
started initially by Harrison Ford who
works with you.
>> That's right.
>> Um
and this year he wasn't there, but it
was hosted by um
by Will and uh Derek Rush Maui and I
think it's
>> Robert Hassold Robert Hassold.
>> Yep. Um spoke on the sort of next
generation crisis of leaders coming up
and and Hassler in particular talked
about the kind of demographic change
coming down the road and um some of the
challenges that's going to present for
us in terms of membership and finances.
And you know, that's a real challenge
that we need to be talking about. I had
a different conversation
um later on in the overtures kind of in
the back with someone kind of on the
other end of the spectrum than me um
and he was talking about the some of the
challenges of churches closing in his
presbytery and or needing assistance and
um not not being able to find pastors to
go there and he was saying, you know, we
need to focus on this is a real problem.
And both of us were like, we're you
know, at that point it was still
overtures meeting and we were like, you
know, we're sitting here arguing about
stuff that is not uh that not that
important. It's a lot of fringe stuff
and we really need to stop talking about
this stuff and start talking about those
mission concerns. And he was like on the
same page about that and that was
encouraging to me because it seems like
this General Assembly as a whole was
kind of like, let's not argue about
those fringe things and let's try to
focus on starting to address our
missional challenges ahead of us. So, I
hope that trend continues.
>> that's what was so encouraging to me
because I think you need to have
GAs like this to be able to allow that
to come more to the foreground. Like,
you know, if we're constantly fighting
the next fight and kind of like this
anxiety that moves us from one to the
other, we won't be able to talk and and
focus on those things that we really
should be talking about talking about
and focusing on. Um and that like for me
the the the fourth you know, like the
one other thing that I had in my mind
was I thought this is a valuable GA and
encouraging GA, but it feels almost like
a prologue to me cuz like
the expectation is we were going to
have, you know, the 90 overtures and
many of those we we we we sent, you
know, sent a few back cuz we weren't
even able to answer, but the reason that
we were specially worried was because we
have these two big,
um, you know, add-in from committees,
these study reports
>> Yeah.
>> that neither neither of which ended up
actually doing a full report. So,
so there's still going to be this
ongoing question. We have a proposed
directory of public worship that was
kind of talked about we've seen
and and and so presumably in Milwaukee
we're going to have to decide are we
going to have a binding directory of
public worship? Can we kind of find
common ground on that? I'm hopeful. Like
I I actually really like the work that
they did. I feel like it's theologically
robust and it kind of defines who we are
as a denomination.
But Milwaukee, that's going to be a big
conversation.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
>> I I guess in some ways actually I didn't
think about this until now, until you
said that, but in some ways both those
study committees had a very similar
spirit in the work they were doing,
which is in many ways to kind of draw
some boundaries around where we already
are and
what identifying things that are kind of
beyond us. And yes, there's diversity
within the PCA, but here's kind of the
and both of them their reports at least
preliminarily preliminarily
You know what I'm trying
>> preliminarily yeah.
>> All right, it's been a long week, but
they both were kind of nodding in that
direction and hopefully that will
continue to be where they land and and
come back next time.
>> Well, I should say the second one just
like we for those who don't know like
Christian nationalism, right? Yes, yeah.
And and we could we sensed I sensed at
least these occasional moments where we
could tell people wanted to talk more
about it. And and there was some anxiety
about it that that generally didn't
actually go much because we really don't
have a chance to talk about it right now
cuz it's not yet the full report.
>> Yeah.
>> So, that you know, like so it's really
going to be interesting to me to see
>> Well, what passion, yeah.
>> Right.
>> But I actually think the way that we're
carrying over both of those reports is
very Presbyterian.
>> Right.
>> Instead of rather than feeling like we
can hash it all out in the the two days
of the General Assembly,
>> Yeah.
>> um we're going to go back to our local
Presbyteries and have those
conversations. We now have 6 months or 9
months or 12 months to have a more
in-depth conversation around the work
that these study committees have done.
>> Yep.
>> Um and you know, I I think we owe it to
our local churches, we owe it to our
Presbyteries to begin to have those
conversations.
>> call for us lately.
>> Yeah. Well, another dimension that will
come at the next Assembly will be we'll
have a new recommendation for a
coordinator for M&A. That's that that
should be here by next year. So, there's
a number of things that are kind of
open-ended.
>> Right.
>> Um we didn't talk a lot about M&A. There
was
coming in a lot of concerns and
questions cuz they've been dealing with
a lot there. Sounds like
they're headed in a good direction
there. Um but yeah, so there's a lot of
open-ended stuff for the next uh General
Assembly for sure.
>> Yep.
>> Any other reflections before we wrap
this up? It sounds like we've covered a
lot of ground here. So, okay. Well,
thanks everyone for tuning in. Uh
hopefully this was helpful just thinking
about what's happened this past week or
informing you uh if you if you weren't
able to be there so you can get a a
little bit of a window into what's
transpired. Um be on the lookout for AMR
resources. We're going to be continuing
to publish on our theological vision in
the coming weeks. We'd love to hear
thoughts and interactions on that. You
can follow us on uh all the social
media, Substack, and uh we have a
different people write for us. And we
really want to start sharing more about
um our missional focus and our focus on
renewal for our denomination. Thanks for
tuning in.